Guide to the Jim Hunt Papers, 1950s-2000s RL.11216
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jim Hunt papers
1950s-2000s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hunt, James D., 1931-2011
RL.11216
8.0 Linear Feet
Dr. Jim D. Hunt was a Professor of Ethics and Religion at Shaw University in Raleigh, NC for almost 30 years. He studied the philosophy of Mohandas K. Gandhi and published several authoritative books on Gandhi, satyagraha, civil rights and peace. The Jim Hunt Papers span the years 1950s-2000s and document Hunt's academic career as a Professor of Religion and his personal life as an activist for social changes. Items in the collection include research materials, correspondence, writings by and about Dr. Hunt, manuscripts, clippings, printed materials, notebooks, information and multimedia packets, photographs, slides, videos and sound recordings, as well as a few artifacts.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Hunt was born in Springfield, Massachusetts, on March 28, 1931. He graduated from East Greenwich, R.I. High School in 1948, Tufts College in 1952, and Boston University in 1958 upon receiving his Masters of Theology. He earned a Ph.D. from Syracuse University in 1965. His thesis was "James Luther Adams and his Demand for an Effective Religious Liberalism.”
In 1968, Shaw University, a predominantly black institution in the South, appointed Dr. Hunt through a civil rights era program. For almost 30 years he was a Professor of Ethics and Religion at Shaw University. In the course of his academic life, Dr. Hunt was also involved in various Civil Rights organizations. He published four books on Mahatma Gandhi and three of them are mentioned in the collection: Gandhi in London, Gandhi and the Nonconformists: Encounters in South Africa, and An American Looks at Gandhi.
Dr. Hunt died on January 12, 2011, in Raleigh, North Carolina. He was 79 years old.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jim Hunt papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016.
Collection Overview
The Jim Hunt Papers span the years 1950s-2000s and document Hunt's academic career as a Professor of Religion and his personal life as an activist for social changes. Items in the collection include research materials, correspondence, writings by and about Dr. Hunt, manuscripts, clippings, printed materials, notebooks, information and multimedia packets, photographs, slides, videos and sound recordings, as well as a few artifacts.
The Research/Subject Files series contains research materials on India and South Africa, writings about Mahatma Gandhi and Martin L. King, book reviews, manuscripts, subject files, photos, and academic papers by Dr. Hunt and others.
The Correspondence series includes personal and professional correspondence received and sent by Dr. Hunt throughout his adult life.
Most of the maps in the Maps series were drawn or collected by Jim Hunt. The bulk of the series was from either India or South Africa.
Passive resistance; Civil rights movements -- United States; Protest movements -- South Africa; Anti-apartheid movements -- South Africa; Hinduism; India -- Maps; India -- Religion; India -- History -- 20th century; Hunt, James D., 1931-2011; Shaw University. Theological Department; Gandhi, Mahatma, 1869-1948; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968
- Research/Subject Files, 1950s-2000s
  Scope and Contents
  xxx
  - India/Hinduism
    - Hinduism (Box 1)
    - Hindu-N.C. (Box 1)
    - India-Unitarians (Box 1)
    - DALITS/ Untouchable, 1970s-2004 (Box 1)
    - Aurobindo, 1970s (Box 1)
    - Hindi-Sanskrit (Box 1)
    - Jainas and Sikhs, 1950s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Vinoba, 1970-1980s (Box 1)
    - Wellock, 1960s-1988 (Box 1)
    - Zoroaster/ Parsis, 1972, 1986, undated (Box 1)
    - Satyagraha: class notes, 1973-1998, undated (Box 1)
    - Nonviolence, 1970s-1989, undated (Box 1)
    - Glass Opera, 1980s (Box 1)
    - Civil disobedience satyagraha, 1963-1992 (Box 1)
    - Hindu/ USA, 1990s, undated (Box 1)
    - Hindu/ USA: movements, groups (Box 1)
    - India, 1970s, 1990s, undated (Box 1)
    - India research, 1966-1974, undated (Box 1)
    - India Perspectives, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous newsletters (Box 1)
    - Modernization of 19th century India (Box 1)
    - Hindu sociology, 1980-1994, undated (Box 1)
    - Temples, 1995-2004, undated (Box 1)
    - Hindu-prints and slides (Box 1)
    - Hindu-Myth, 1979-1992, undated (Box 1)
    - Hindu-basic notes, 1990s-2000s (Box 1)
  - South Africa
    - South Africa, 1960-1985, undated (Box 1)
    - South Africa: Administration TVL Cencus (Box 1)
    - South Africa structure: economy, labor (Box 1)
    - South Africa, 1977 (Box 1)
    - South Africa: Extrajudicial execution, 1990s (Box 1)
    - South Africa: Churches and race, 1970s-1990s (Box 1)
    - South Africa: Travel, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - South Africa: prints, 1977, undated (Box 1)
  - Organizations
    - Association for Asian Studies (AAS)-San Francisco, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Indian Opinion papers (Box 1)
    - Gandhi's Editor (Box 1)
    - South Asia Group, 1990-1999 (Box 1)
    - Greenleaf Books, 1979-1980s, 2000-2001, undated (Box 1)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH), 1972-1982 (Box 1)
  - Mahatma K Gandhi
    - Important articles on M.K.Gandhi (Box 2)
    - Herman Kallenbach Diary (Box 2)
    - Mayo: writings on Tolstoy (Box 2)
    - Tolstoy Texts (Box 2)
    - Ferdinands (Box 2)
    - A. Maude, 1990s-2000s (Box 2)
    - Tolstoy and Gandhi on Sex, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Wolpert: "Gandhi's Passion", 2001 (Box 2)
    - Book reviews (Box 2)
    - Hocking: "Belinda the Backward" (Box 2)
    - Transcriptions from India libraries (Box 2)
    - Biography (Box 2)
    - Search lists (Box 2)
    - Research guides (Box 2)
    - Hind Swaraj sources (Box 2)
    - Anthony Parel on Hind Swaraj, 1992-1998 (Box 2)
    - Public Record Office (PRO) and Parliamentary papers (Box 2)
    - Stephen Hay history papers, 1972-1990 (Box 2)
    - Stephen Hay papers, 1975-2000 (Box 2)
    - Pyarelal-Manuscript plan (Box 2)
    - D.H. Butani: "Resurrection of Gandhi", undated (Box 2)
    - Sriram Mehrotra (Box 2)
    - Book Lists, 1993, 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Gandhi Biography, 1955-1970, undated (Box 2)
    - Arrival of M.K. Gandhi in South Africa, 1893-1894 (Box 2)
    - Gandhi-to 1888 (Box 2)
    - Gandhi in India-from 1915 (Box 2)
    - Gandhi and Thoreau (Box 2)
    - John Haynes Holmes: Gandhi in Unity (Box 2)
    - Bibliography and writings on Gandhi (Box 2)
    - Teaching material from "Gandhi" film, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Gandhi-Teaching unit (Box 2)
    - Study of MKG, 1980s (Box 2)
    - Gandhi, 1969-1983 (Box 2)
    - Gandhi-Life, 1967-1997 (Box 2)
    - Gandhi-Life lecture notes, 1981-1985 (Box 2)
    - Gandhi-notes chronology (Box 2)
    - Gandhi-Myth, 1973-1987 (Box 2)
    - MKG-misc, 1964-1990, undated (Box 2)
    - Gandhi Newsletters, 1969, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Trusteeship-MKG, undated (Box 2)
    - Leo Tolstoy Texts (Box 2)
    - D.M.Manilal Texts, 1911-1913 (Box 2)
    - Thambi Naidoo, 1965-2000 (Box 2)
    - E.S.Reddy's Papers, 1988-1995 (Box 2)
    - Dr. P.J.Metha Texts, 1970s (Box 2)
    - Arun Gandhi, 1985-1999 (Box 2)
    - Uma Duphelia Texts, 1981-1994 (Box 2)
    - Polak Texts, 1990s-2000s (Box 2)
    - Gandhi-U.S.A (Box 2)
    - Reddy-Gandhi Letters to Americans, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Reddy-Gandhi and America, 1994; 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Nazar-letter book, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Nazar (Box 4)
    - The British ethical societies:Mackillop, Ian Duncan, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Huttenback Papers (Box 5)
  - Martin Luther King and MKG
    - MLK and MKG (Box 3)
    - M.L.King-Campaigns, 1960s-1980s (Box 3)
    - M.L.King-Family education, 1960s-1990s (Box 3)
    - Gandhi and King comparisons, 1977-1983 (Box 3)
    - M.L.King-Life (Box 3)
  - Book Reviews
    - Gandhi in London-comments, 1975-1990s (Box 3)
    - G.I.L-correspondence about reviews, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
    - G.I.L-reviews (Box 3)
    - G.I.L-Name lists (Box 3)
    - Gandhi and The Nonconformists-Book review, 1980s (Box 3)
    - Gandhi and The Nonconformists-review (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Papers
    - Misc Papers (1 of 2) (Box 3)
    - Misc Papers (2 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Manuscripts
    - Manuscripts (Box 3)
    - Memo (original), 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - Note Book, undated (Box 3)
  - Photos/Paintings
    - Gandhi photo book (Box 3)
    - Origami Buddha (Box 3)
    - South Africa negatives and proofs, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Paintings and sculptures on MKG (Box 3, Oversize-folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Booklets (Box 3)
    - India-pictures (Box 3)
    - Natal places (Box 3)
  - Slides and Media
    - Phonodiscs, 1961-1969 and undated; 3 items 3 phonodiscs (Item PD 1, Item PD 2, Item PD 3)
      Includes: Gandhi: Man on Trial (BBC, 1969); India I (A Musical Anthology of the Orient); and Hindi Language Record Course (Conversa-Phone Institute, 1961).
    - Film Strips (Box 6)
      Includes 4 titles (6 reels total): The Story of Bapu (3 rolls); Glimpses of India (1 roll); Gandhi f.s. (1 roll); and Gandhi movie filmstrip (1 roll)
    - Slide sets (Box 6)
      Includes personal and published sets collected by Hunt including topics such as India, Hinduism, Gandhi, South Africa, London, and other images related to Hunt's research and teaching. Some are captioned.
- Audio cassettes (Box 6)
  Includes 5 cassettes: Talk with Prabhudas Gandhi on 29/1/92 at Rashtriy Ashala, Rajkot about the relation of the Phoenix settlers to native Africans; BBC Program on Gandhi; Filmstrip soundtrack: Gandhi (2 versions); National Youth Camp., India.
- Card files (Box 6)
  2 card file boxes: Religions; Nazav letterbook calls/Early Phoenix settlers/Hinduism/1931 London
- Writings
  - James Hunt's writings
    - Papers, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Paper in Indo-British Review, 1979, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Article: MK Gandhi in South Africa, 1977 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1970s-2000s
  - Sushila Nayar, 1985-2001 (Box 4)
  - Surendra Bhana, 1980s-2005 (Box 4)
  - E.S.Reddy, 1993-1998 (Box 4)
  - Toronto/brock, 1984-1991 (Box 4)
  - Dennis Dalton, 1975-1990s (Box 4)
  - South Africa, 1978-1993 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence (Box 4)
  - Haridas Muzumdar, 1977-1982 (Box 4)
  - Michael Johnson (Box 4)
  - Ian LeMaistre, 1977-1982 (Box 4)
  - Stephen Hay (Box 4)
  - Dr.Sarid, 1990s-2000s (Box 4)
  - Martin Green, 1970s, 1990s (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, 1978, 1980s-1990s (Box 4)
  - Stephen Murphy, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
  - Burnett Britton (Box 4)
  - Myron Phelps (Box 4)
  - Durban Library letter (Box 4)
- Maps, 1957-1990s
  - India maps and technology assessment, 1970s (Box 5, Oversize-folder 1)
  - Natal-Durban, 1970s (Box 5)
  - Johannesburg (JHB), 1980s (Box 5)
  - MKG-Battlefield (Box 5)
  - JHB, 1919 (Box 5)
  - Zulu (Box 5)
  - PreToria, undated (Box 5)
  - Transvaal and Johannesburg, 1980s-1990s (Box 5)
  - Natal (Box 5)
  - Gujarat (Box 5)
  - Namibia, undated (Box 5)
  - Southern Asia, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Gandhi in England (Box 5)